[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of the attitude that one should have when beginning to look into the suttas, to start the path, to try to understand what the Buddha is saying, is that one must understand that you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that is pretty much prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that seems to be overlooked, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because most people start off with, I know quite a bit already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: They start with, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as soon as they get to know something, that becomes, oh, now I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody starts, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the first port of call I become familiar with, oh, I read this sutta, or I heard from that teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now that already gave me a basis, which is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become more familiar.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the slightest sort of familiarity then gets conceived as knowledge, misconceived as knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now I'm familiar with it, and you immediately start assuming that that's now you know what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, again, to give an example, say you don't know anything, you heard about Buddhism, seems interesting, you want to learn to meditate, want to free yourself from suffering, maybe in whatever vague terms,
[SPEAKER_01]: You relate to that thought, and then you go, I don't know, and listen to a talk from some Theravāda monk, and then you start reading the suttas, and now you know more, you're more familiar, you've got more information.
[SPEAKER_01]: Information is not the knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, have you understood it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, yes, I understood it to some degree, because I make sense out of it, I can explain to somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine, but that is mundane.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not even the beginning of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't forsake the mundane idea of understanding, you will not then develop the supramundane, which is the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: The understanding that frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is the beginning of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing the Four Noble Truths, as those very same suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here you are, thinking you're understanding, because you're familiar with it, you read it so many times, you have all the information, all the etymology.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're overlooking the fact that, yeah, but do I know the way out of suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of this is great, but have... if I were to understand one sutta, let alone many, I would be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I were to understand in the way that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you use the same word for understanding, as in if you... well, that's understanding, but also my...
[SPEAKER_01]: Familiarity with of information is also understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then you will not push yourself into that understanding that will free you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you somehow believe that understanding of information pertains to understanding from a way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no linear, uh, guaranteed, sort of, step by step.
[SPEAKER_01]: You read this sutta, then read this sutta, then read that sutta, and then you sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, how did you become a Sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by understanding what Sotāpanna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you need some information to start, as in to know where to think, in what direction to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, unless you make that effort, regardless of the information, and certainly not impeded by thinking understanding of information is the understanding of the freedom from suffering, then you will make that effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about not reading the suttas because I end up thinking I understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's another problem now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how do you know what to understand if you're not reading the instruction from the Buddha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you want to do is keep reading the suttas, keep listening to the talks, but keep reflecting upon it to the point of, if you were to understand it, you will be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not being free from suffering, as in free from liability to suffer, not just, oh yes, it helped me deal with something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It helped me not experience suffering amidst the same circumstances that used to cause me to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That should be the norm.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the bare minimum, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only reason people don't seek that as a bare minimum is because they deny that that's a bare minimum.
[SPEAKER_01]: They lower the bar even more and say, no, familiarity of understanding, familiarity of information, and I get my head around it, that's already the minimum.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The minimum is being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: The minimum is not being still subjected to possibility of, you know, peril, if you are reborn in a lower realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the minimum is the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, one who has the right view, is the one who sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, without the right view, you are not seeing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you be saying your familiarity of information that talks about dhamma, is understanding of the dhamma to some extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know what is right and wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: What teaching is right, what is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've got no idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to keep reading the suttas, you want to keep listening to the talks, but you also want to be reflecting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're not being free from suffering, it's due to... it's only possible because of the two... there can only be two reasons for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either the instruction that you're listening is wrong, or you're not properly attending to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or both.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess there is a third.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or both.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so is this instruction correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I can't quite tell, but I can use my intelligence to narrow it down, which is least likely to be wrong, the instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's always like lean towards the suttas, talks either about the suttas, they will push you into reading suttas, because that is, again, you don't know for sure the suttas are right either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to start somewhere, and that is least likely to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the best you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so now, the suttas are least likely to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Done deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, but now you have to start working.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you're very familiar.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, you're making lots of sense with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are you being freed from liability to suffer, even before the suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that understanding resulting in you being unable to experience dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like hiding from the dukkha or avoiding things.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm simply unable, even amidst things that used to cause me to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind cannot experience it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the water just falls off those leaves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this sutta, Majjhima Nikaya 70, Buddha says, I do not say that final knowledge, actual knowledge, is achieved all at once.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, final knowledge is achieved by gradual training, by gradual practice, by gradual progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how is this done?
[SPEAKER_00]: One who has faith in a teacher...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the gradual training?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: One who has faith in a teacher visits him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, faith in the teacher corresponds to, okay, who's least likely to be wrong based on my discerning capabilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I don't know where out of suffering, but
[SPEAKER_01]: I have my intelligence intact, I can think for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is least likely to be wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you seek out.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you find out what is least likely to be wrong, what seems to be pertaining to that which might free you from suffering, you put faith in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for its own sake, not as its own goal, but just faith in terms of, okay, I'll apply this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, like choosing a medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can... oh, this... this is least... this is most promising medicine, but you will never know, unless you start applying it and following the instructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: A particular diet, a particular lifestyle, avoiding certain things, so the medicine can start to work.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, you need to wait.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to keep doing it, gradually, until then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like... the measure of medicine working is then the measure of, ah, I'm healing from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Healing from the possibility to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the true freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you know that you can't suffer, even amidst things that would make everybody else suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you learn to focus on your nostrils, or you learn to do this, the quick to respond.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply, you're abandoned craving through understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're unable to suffer, regardless of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point that the Buddha said, if you're an arahant, you would have, you could have robbers chopping up your limbs, one by one, like utter savages, and you will not experience dukkha on that account.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not hate them, you will not have any aversion in your mind towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the gradual teaching begins with that faith that is a prerequisite for the application of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not faith that's a prerequisite for this superstitious belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: That now I chant the suttas, and I read the suttas, and I bow to the suttas, and I have the unwavering faith that the Buddha was right, although I don't know for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the faith we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the faith you have in a doctor.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's some proper quacks, then there's some somebody who seems more knowledgeable, then somebody who seems more knowledgeable, and wise as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you choose wisely yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to apply some medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then maybe say, okay, this doctor helped me to some extent, but have I applied the medication correctly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Have I really understood
[SPEAKER_01]: So, always twofold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, the instruction, but not just, oh, he might be saying wrong things, but have I actually really understood this to full extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's even what the Buddha himself did before he became the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he was with different teachers, he would then go and
[SPEAKER_01]: You present back to them what he understood, and there we go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, that's exactly what I'm teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are equal to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come, sit.
[SPEAKER_01]: We lead this community together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your understanding is exactly where I'm... And the Buddha says, OK, thank you, but that's not enough for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, have you understood that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you choose, oh, this is wrong, you want to know why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say you start following some doctor, some dhammatalk, whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you're not being free from suffering, and then you decide it's wrong, because now you find something better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be that as it may, do you know how, why, to what extent was this wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you understood it, you would know that it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are you just dismissing it as wrong, because it stopped inspiring you, because you got lazy, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's right or wrong, needs to be understood as right or as wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it can be understood if you keep applying that effort to understand the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the instruction here?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the goal here?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the teaching here?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the implications here?
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that you can develop or even invest effort if you haven't had faith to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're just looking for faults in all the doctors, yeah, that seems pretty good, but meh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not applying anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're truly in a position to choose right and wrong, you wouldn't need doctors to be helping you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why first and foremost is, wait, I need help.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me not think that I know, when I don't, because if I do know, I would be free from suffering and I wouldn't need any instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, time might be short, so don't spend too much time picking and choosing, but instead discern
[SPEAKER_01]: Apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a person could go, you know, pretty much anywhere, really, you know, some monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to figure out, is it right or is it wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you understand that it's wrong, that would be to your benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that would be your rightness.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would benefit you, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even when I say to people, sometimes they ask for a monastery to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, really, all you need is a monastery where, like, say, they will not be forcing views and books on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, if you read anything that deviates from this, you'll be expelled, because there are places like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if they're all... he's into suttas, or he's into whatever...
[SPEAKER_01]: This teacher or that teacher, as long as, I suppose, Buddhist, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they let you study on your own, do your own study, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the place keeps the vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if everything else is, oh yeah, they have these views, and senior monks have such views, and wrong views, none of that is your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, now you're worrying about the state of the medical profession in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You only need a doctor that knows that you can apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can't find the one that knows directly, well, find the instruction from those who knew.
[SPEAKER_01]: And keep... need environment to keep applying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Environment where you can keep the vinaya, have enough solitude, and keep studying to the point of developing understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means study.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean just study.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And collect information.
[SPEAKER_01]: But make effort to reflect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, many of the monasteries would meet the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you will have pointless tasks and duties, but none of that is really a fundamental issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless, of course, you spend 20 hours of your day doing meaningless things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just continue with that gradual... Yeah, so the faith...
[SPEAKER_00]: He visits, visits that person that he has faith in.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he can.
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, he googles it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He pays respects to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He gives ear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gives ear means what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't look for faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's full stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to learn how not to look, how not to confuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, looking for faults tends to be confused for discriminating.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I tell you don't look for faults, okay, so I must stop discriminating.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still look right is right, wrong is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to discern, see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just don't look for faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't make your discrimination personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you won't be looking for faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's really what fault finding is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sole problem is to understand what's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's wrong, to understand why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it feels right, to understand why it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't make it personal, you will not look for faults.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're saying something wrong, I will not be, ah, he's wrong, he's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just, what's being said doesn't fit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I understand to this extent that it doesn't fit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you might tell me back that I misunderstood you, and then you'd explain, in and out, but maybe you will then learn something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I just look for faults, means I haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why you are wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: The wrongness of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I put myself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, by looking for faults in you, I imply I'm better.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even what you're expressing, if it's wrong, it's not a personal thing for you either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or if it is for you, it doesn't need to be my personal thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you might be taking personally, but it's not my problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't look for faults means be open to hear what's being said without the kind of, sort of, a bit of a reserve, like, hmm... You have no criteria what fits and what's truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to really commit to the instruction and understand it fully, through and through.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if it were wrong, it would become evident without needing to make it personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, oh, the instruction was wrong because there is such and such discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I understood the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I can explain it, because I understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I used to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, go to the library in the monastery, like, books of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not any kind, but, I mean, like, Buddhism, but from all sorts of the very broad spectrum of teachers and traditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are certain things that you kind of know obviously are wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I would take those books, because it's not enough just, oh, this is wrong, because it's a different tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to understand, as I start reading it, why this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to explain to myself and to others, if somebody were to ask me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, see, Nagarjuna view was wrong for such and such reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, he's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he's wrong, means he might, he must be contradicting at some point, some aspect of the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm not like fishing for... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you understand it fully, because he might be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's frightening, especially in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It fills you with anxiety, because, oh, this is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you start thinking, well, what if I don't see it as wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, that's the real risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means then, what you think you understood, you haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't run away from that anxiety, and accept it, and then read through it, then you realize, actually, that is the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm undoing my own mistaken notions, through understanding wrong view as wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm developing my own correct notions by understanding right view as right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I were looking for faults, ah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just read the moment it displeases me, it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would never understand wrong is wrong, which means I would never understand right is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your criteria for right and wrong is just how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fully emotional, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As always, you haven't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have refined it, but fundamentally it's still simply based in how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's not the criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like Theravāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the criteria, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why do you like Theravāda?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know, because the first retreat I went was Theravāda, and I liked the feeling, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, by the way, for the same reason, people like the non-Theravāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: They went into that direction and, like, oh no, this is... this is my path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what is the path?
[SPEAKER_01]: Path is that which frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you can be in Theravāda and not be on the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be non-Theravāda and not be on the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, the only way you'll be on the path is if you actually are understanding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have that right criteria, whereby understanding of wrong is wrong and right is right, frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wrong view is wrong view, right view is right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to what extent Sotāpanna is free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mountain Himalayas,
[SPEAKER_01]: And seven grains of sand are left.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how much suffering Sotāpanna has abolished.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mountains of Himalayas suffering he's abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: All he has left is these seven grains of sand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how much he has left.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see how profound right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can take that further and abandon these seven grains of sand as well, become an arahant, and you have to, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, right view is not a joke, and it's not something you get on account of information, but at the same time, it's not this impossibility either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have your senses intact?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you, like, intellectually sound?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you think for yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you restrain yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're aware of your choices?
[SPEAKER_01]: No excuse, then, for not getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suttas are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Read it, ponder upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize the thing that impedes you is what you just read.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not the lack of instruction, or this, or, oh, they're making me do these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your lack of faith, looking for faults, lack of respect, lack of application.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you carry on, you realize, ah, so it's this thing, and they're fully dependent upon you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can then choose to abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just read it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says here, he pays respects, he gives ear, he listens to what's being said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then he hears the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having heard the dhamma, he memorizes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He examines the meaning of the teachings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Examines the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, how often that gets overlooked today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, knowing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The knowing is now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I know that I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: What have you understood?
[SPEAKER_01]: Please, explain to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I can't put it into words.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no understanding then.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the way the monks back in the day would know whether they are kind of on the right path or not, is they get other monks to question them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they explain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the ones who understood would say, yeah, yeah, what you're saying is basically right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They know what this person's talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So examine the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing mystical about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I had this experience and, you know, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's out of this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is out of this world?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean by experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the Buddha teaching that liberation comes out of the experience from out of this world?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or comes out of full understanding upon examining the meaning?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, full understanding upon examining the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter what experience you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is whether you understood it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, examining the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you examining the meaning?
[SPEAKER_01]: After you lend your ear, not looking for faults, out of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so now, day in, day out, my practice is examining the meaning to the point of understanding these universal truths, the dhamma, that frees me from liability to suffer, let alone any suffering right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without that...
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot gain a reflective acceptance of those teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't gain an understanding if you do not examine the meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just magically, somehow...
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, after gaining an understanding,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Effort springs up.
[SPEAKER_00]: When effort springs up, he applies his will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can think about, like, oh, you need to do... you need to fix something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have this idea that you need to fix, but you have no clue how to go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you feel towards that prospect?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, like... Because you don't really know what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know how to fix it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even know exactly what needs fixing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then imagine, ah...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what needs fixing, and this is how you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do it right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You immediately get inspiration to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you know what needs to be done, and you know what needs to be done, because you have reflexively understood what needs to be done, and you have reflexively understood what needs to be done, because you made the effort to understand the meaning of what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like I need to find the zeal now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be the result of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The path is clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have no zeal, it means you lack understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you do not have energy for practice, it means you haven't understood it enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, but I can't practice because I don't have the energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you don't have the energy because you're not practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will get the energy if you start making the effort to understand, which will then start increasing the clarity of what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Energy will be the result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: A lot of people actually say that I don't have the energy for practice anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're... You've never had it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because energy, vidya, properly, is effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based upon mindfulness, it's the result of your correct seeing and understanding the meaning that you pondered upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: The result of having... That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: A tireless energy arose in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even when they just talk on dhamma, the result of just that talk would be tireless energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: He applies his will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having applied his will, he scrutinizes, he resolutely strives.
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole tirelessly striving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tireless, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have a clear sight of what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent, you don't have energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you see the path that needs to be walked, to freedom... You'll be running.
[SPEAKER_00]: For freedom from suffering, you'll be running.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the same, for the same reason, I mean, a slight kind of detail, but for the same reason, it's said that a noble disciple does not free himself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like Sotāpanna Sakadāgāmī doesn't quite become anāgāmī yet, because he lacks faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he has understood that he got the right view, understood the way out of suffering, but there are still these residues of sensuality, ill-will, that now he needs to clarify the meaning of those even more, and if he does so, the energy, resoluteness towards overcoming sensuality will be the result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he doesn't do that because he doesn't really develop faith in those directions, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you found a doctor, he cured you, you see for yourself now what health is, but there's still some lingering symptoms that pop up, bother you, disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, from your overall view of general health, you're not terminal anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, from the point of view of itself, it's still something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still these ailments that come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you just need to develop faith a bit further,
[SPEAKER_01]: And start treating those ailments as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that the energy... Then, once you get to know how to deal with the ailments, on account of reflecting upon it, thinking upon it, the energy will be effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: But isn't... isn't that with all life's goals?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is... ah, that's how you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that in those, like, you know, genetic sort of motivational quotes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just people don't even think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you think about it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I could actually do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity of your...
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you think, the more you ponder, the clearer it becomes what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it starts with that attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why it's also important to come across the right instruction that tells you this.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I just tell you, oh, no, practice of dhamma, it's about non-understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you practice, the less you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you know, I heard people say, as a teaching, like, that's completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, okay, so it's about not knowing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I must start forgetting even things I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you think that's what the practice is, well, you found a really bad doctor, who's not a doctor, who's not just not curing you, he's basically making you more sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now, you think that's what dhamma is, and you spend the rest of your life applying the non-knowing of whatever else contradictions you picked up, thinking you're practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But we haven't, if you reflected properly enough...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you reflected properly enough, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just started reading the suttas, you'd see, wait, this doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But some people... Yeah, maybe he meant this, maybe it doesn't matter, I will not listen to that doctor, because he's not careful with his instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, oh, yes, yes, I meant this, but I said the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which self-respecting doctor would do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, don't go out in the sun.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the heat can harm you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, instead, I tell you, there is no heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no cold.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is heat, and there is cold, and there are the effects of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They could make your illness worse or better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a doctor you should listen to, because he doesn't know what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: He himself, obviously, is not cured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he were, why would he tell you the opposite?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's impossible to do the dhamma rightly, practice correctly, understood rightly, and not get the results of it, not be cured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the simile of the the chick with the hen that sits on its eggs.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the hand sits on her eggs, even if she doesn't wish for her chicks to come up and pierce out safely, they will, because she's doing the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other hand doesn't sit on the eggs, even if she does wish, may my chicks pierce out safely into this wall, they won't, because she's not sitting on the eggs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're sitting on the eggs, in terms of if you're doing the practice, the result will have to come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Results of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Freedom from liability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The results, they're the results in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, oh, I feel much better about myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the result of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just the result of you making some sort of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is great.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not the threshold, not the bar you need to be... you want to be striving for.